<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The burthen of the ministerie Gathered out of the sixt chapiter of the Epistles of S. Paul to the Galathians, the first verse. Verie profitable to be read of euery faithfull subiect, and of all that desire to be taught in the waie of truth. By Iohn Holme.</title>
            <author>Holme, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852453</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852453</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17777</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 346:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The burthen of the ministerie Gathered out of the sixt chapiter of the Epistles of S. Paul to the Galathians, the first verse. Verie profitable to be read of euery faithfull subiect, and of all that desire to be taught in the waie of truth. By Iohn Holme.</title>
                  <author>Holme, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Danter for Iohn Winnington,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The verse number is cited erroneously as 'first' on the title page, correctly as '5' on B1r.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (-F4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BVRTHEN OF THE <hi>MINISTERIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gathered out of the ſixt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of the Epiſtle of S. Paul to the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians, the firſt verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERIE PROFITABLE TO BE read of euery faithfull ſubiect, and of all that deſire to be taught in the waie of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By IOHN HOLME.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Math. 11.29.30.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Take my yoke vpon you, for my burthen is light</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. Danter</hi> for <hi>Iohn Winnington.</hi> 1592.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE</hi> George Earle of Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Baron Clifford, Lord Bromflet, Aton <hi>and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſcie, &amp;c. Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter:</hi> IOHN HOLME <hi>wiſheth increaſe of all honour.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat no doubt (Right honorable) are the blowes which our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the Papiſts haue giuen vs, and yet our Church not once moueth or giueth place to the traditions of men: But yet in this notable victory and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer them, we may well be compared to a company of ſouldiors, who hauing gotten a pray, and falling foorth amongſt themſelues for the diuiſion of it, in the meane time the enemie comes, and ſpoiles them all, and takes it quite from them. Wee of England haue in peace poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed
<pb facs="tcp:17777:3"/> the word of truth a long time, but about vnneceſſary trifles we are readie to go together by the eares; a ſtrange matter, that out of light ſhould ſpring ſuch palpable darkneſſe, and that our Miniſterie ſhould trauell as it were of ſects. Well, let vs take heed, that while we thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume one another, hee take not this iewell (for which the Merchant ſold all that he had to buy it) and giue it to a Nation that will bring forth the fruites thereof. Though the watchmen ſitte on the tower, and tell vs daily they eſpie immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat daungers; yea, though his preachers tell vs deſtruction will bee to Iuda, and deſolation to Ieruſalem, yet we care not for the ſafetie of our country, nor for the pretious Goſpell which we would ſeeme to profeſſe, our conſciences are ſeared vp; and the ſpirite of pride hath got the dominion ouer vs, which a learned Father ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the cauſe of ſchiſme and diſſention.</p>
            <p>In this little Booke (Right Honourable) I haue preſcribed a potion to cure ſuch a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous diſeaſe, the qualitie thereof you ſhall bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perceiue if you reade it through: and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I preſume of your honor, for that of a child you haue beene ready to benefite the Church, beeing a father to the fatherleſſe and widowe, a reſtorer of the Leuites portion, a defier of the world, and a chiefe defender of our Nation, that
<pb facs="tcp:17777:3"/> night and day haue beene in the perill of ſea, in perill of robbers, yea ſometime with Paule in peril of death and that for our ſafety, who liue at reſt, eating the fruits of our labours in peace therefore ſince pouertie cannot giue to honour the thinges of this worlde, yet ſuch as we haue with Peter that will we giue: beſeeching your Honour the rather to accept of it, becauſe it proceeded from a willing minde, and from a faithfull Northren heart, and thus I leaue it to your godly conſideration, to whome our Vniuerſitie is bounde in weightier matters.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours to command <hi>IOHN HOLME.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian people straite is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth to eternall life, &amp; few there be that enter into it: but broad is the waye that leadeth to deſtruction, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there be that finde it out, and walke in it: the one way full of pleaſure and eaſe, the other crabbed, croked and full of ſorrow. And this is the waye of the Church and choſen people of God, <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt be vnder <hi>Egypt,</hi> the three Children in the fyrie fornace, <hi>Dauid</hi> must be perſecuted in his owne kingdome, by his owne ſonne, and Chriſt himſelfe muſt be crucified: No maruaile therefore though the Deuill ſow contentions in our mindes, now wee being at reſt, for that euen in peace we ſhould begin to warre, for the reforming of which miſchiefe many and ſundrie Pamphelets haue been written, but either wee are to deafe that we can not heare, or els to negligent in practiſing thoſe thinges that we heare: neuer ſo much preaching God be praiſed neuer ſo little profitting, the Lord amend it, Some
<pb facs="tcp:17777:4"/> of vs haue itching eares, to heape to our ſelues a number of teachers, and with ſome of vs it is mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, we care for no teachers, the one ſorte be the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> the other be the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Geſuits</hi> of our time. And though our moſt gratious Queen whoſe life the Lord long continue, as the faithfull witnes in heauen, do labour and ſtriue, to ſet peace betwene <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> betwene Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Miniſtery: yet we diſloiall ſeruaunts to ſo good a gouernour, flee farre from this peace. Was euer any land guided ſo well and wiſely? yet behold the enuious ſoweth tares in the mindes of her loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſubiects, to driue them from obedience. Theſe &amp; ſuch like are the trials, which perſuade my hart of the trueth of the religion of England: For this cauſe thou haſte here (gentle Reader) the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the miniſterie, wherin is ſet downe the cauſes of contentious and ſciſmes, lately ſprung vp amongeſt vs, deſiring when thou knoweſt them to eſchew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and now to become true to her Maiestie, if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore thou hast not beene ſound, ſo God will bleſſe thee for thy true <hi>Iſraëlites</hi> heart, and guide thee in all thy waies, that thy foot daſh not againſt a ſtone, and at the laſt bring thee to euerlaſting life through the merits of Christ</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours Io. Holme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:5"/>
            <head>THE BVRTHEN OF <hi>THE <hi>MINISTERIE.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GAL. 6. VERSE. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For euerie man ſhall beare his owne burthen.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle in the beginning of this Chapter exhorting the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians to the ſpirite of lenitie, that rather they ſhoulde admoniſh a brother by infirmitie falling, then raſhly to condemne him for an Atheiſt or a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate: which hee prooueth by foure argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe they ſhould conſider them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues how weake they were of themſelues, leaſt the Lorde alſo giue them ouer to bee tempted.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe in ſo doing they did ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the lawe, euen the lawe of loue, which cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably commandeth them to thinke of their brethren.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe it would make them haue
<pb facs="tcp:17777:6"/> a fond conceit of themſelues, to thinke better of themſelues than indeed they were.</p>
            <p>The fourth and the principall reaſon is laide downe in theſe ſhort words; <hi>For euerie man ſhal beare his owne burthen:</hi> and therefore be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, mild, and gentle. A doctrine ſo neceſſary, that without it the man of God can neuer bee made perfect, nor euer come to the wiſhed ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, but periſh in the midſt of the ſea by bloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous and moſt troubleſome tempeſts. And as it is impoſſible to walke without a legge, or to bee valiant in war without armour or wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons: ſo he that is not furniſhed with this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, let him neuer flatter himſelfe, for he will but proue a daſtard in the field, and fall downe before his enemies to his own vtter ouerthrow in helfire for euer. But I thinke it better for you and me, and more profitable to ſet downe the principles, whereof I intend now to ſpeake, which are two.</p>
            <p>Firſt I will prooue vnto you that euerie one hath a burthen: Secondly, that euery one muſt beare his owne burthen.</p>
            <p>For the firſt it were a large theame to handle and many volumes might bee ſpent in writing of it: you know that all we which bee the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> are ſinners, and this ſin is a burthen,</p>
            <p>The latter propoſition may be prooued by
<pb facs="tcp:17777:6"/> many places: as is <hi>Eſay</hi> the firſt; <hi>Onus Moab;</hi> the burthen of <hi>Moab:</hi> and what is it but the ſinne of <hi>Moab? Iudas</hi> his ſinne was ſuch a burthen, ſo heauie that hee could not beare it, but moſt deſperately by hanging himſelfe, was the cauſe of the ſhortening of his daies. The like is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by that diueliſh image of ſin <hi>Caine,</hi> whoſe ſinne was ſo greeuous, that one day ſcarce was he able to beare it. VVhich thing the blinde Philoſophers did know and well perceiue: as <hi>Cato; Nemo ſine crimine viuit:</hi> None liues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a fault. No man is without this burthen (as <hi>Iuuenal</hi> ſaith) <hi>Nemo ſapit omnibus horis.</hi> This is proued alſo in <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. VVhen the Lord ſawe that the wickednes of man was great vpon the earth, and all the imaginations of the thoughtes of his hart were onely euill continually. VVith this agreeth the ſaying of <hi>Dauid; There is none that doth good no not one, for they are corrupt, and become abhominable in their doings.</hi> So that (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) the wiſe man is without his works, and the yoong man without obedience. VVe haue a figure in Rhetorike, called <hi>hiſteron proteron,</hi> and yet no figure now a dayes, becauſe it is the truth it ſelfe. The ſhippe which by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the waues is toſſed hither and thither, and ſtaggereth, as the Prophet ſaith, like a dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken man by contrarie winds, by reaſon wherof
<pb facs="tcp:17777:7"/> the ſhippe it ſelfe is turned vp ſide downe, and the men that were in it, in the ſeas moſt pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ouerwhelmed. The ſhippe of the worlde by the waues of wickedneſſe is turned vp ſide downe; the heauen that was aboue, is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and the earth which was belowe, is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue; wiſedome is follie, and follie is wiſdome; Loue, which was a couer for ſinne, and as ſtrong as the graue, is now as weake as water, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth all ſinne; Charitie, which was hot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, is now quite frozen vp for want of heate; fleſhly heartes become flintie, and as hard as ſteele; yea true religion, and vndefiled before God, is counterfaite religion, and goes for no currant money with ſome in England: ſo that either wee haue good heads to walke with our feet vpwards, or elſe we can but looke for a ſodaine deſtruction, as the Sodomites, who were ſo drunken with ſinne, that they coulde not tell where they were, but you knowe their puniſhment, a moſt iuſt iudgement, and I pray God that it light not on vs for our ſins heere in England like vnto Sodome, yea worſe than Gomorrha, who for our pride haue deſerued the loweſt place in hell, and for our couetouſnes to bee puniſhed with penurie, as was the riche man in the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>But to come a little more nearely to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:17777:7"/> of my text: although theſe greeuous ſinnes be a burthen to England, ſo that we had neede to waſh our ſelues with Iſope, that we might be whiter than ſnow, as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt was, yet wee will leaue this, and come to more neceſſary matter. <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> brings in a good concluſion. <hi>1. Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> 2. Vanitie of vanities, all is vanitie, and what greater burthen is there than vanitie? Yea, what profit hath a man of all his labour vnder the Sun? one generation paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, another ſucceedeth, and the earth remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, all things are troubleſome and painefull, no man can vtter them. The eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, the eare is not filled with hearing, and this is a burthen: And to conclude (ſayth <hi>Salomon</hi>) I haue ſeene all things vnder the Sun. But behold they are all vanitie and vexation of ſpirit, ſo that ye ſee the vanitie of this life is ſuch a heauie and weariſome burthen, that a man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt can take no ioye in this world. But more particularly in theſe our dayes ſchiſms and ſects are great and heauy burthens, indeede it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie that there ſhould be ſuch, but wo vnto that man by whom offences doe come.</p>
            <p>By which things we may gather that theſe be the laſt times, and the dangerous daies, wherof our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtle Paul pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecieth full truely, for the firſt we read in the
<pb facs="tcp:17777:8"/> 24. Mat. <hi>Many ſhal come in my name, I am chriſt will they ſay, and ſhall deceiue many.</hi> And in the 24. verſe, <hi>falſe Christs, and faiſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes &amp; wonders,</hi> ſo that if it wer poſſible they ſhould deceiue the verie elect. If any man then ſhall ſay vnto yon this is Chriſt, beleeue him not, for beholde I haue tolde you before: but conſider I pray you the 3. chap. of the 2. Epiſtle to Timothie, where he dooth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and ſet the ſects in their colors: for men ſhall be louers of themſelues. In the 2. verſe without natural affection; in the 3. Traitors; in the 4. hauing a ſhew of godlines; but haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the power thereof, in the 5. But in the next ver. are they moſt liuely pictured out, for of this ſorte are they which creepe into houſes, &amp; lead captiue ſimple women laden with ſins, and led with diuers luſts. In the 6. and in the 8 verſe he compareth them to Iannes and I am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, who refuſed Moſes, but they ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile no longer, for their madnes ſhall bee eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vnto all men,: and in the 10. verſe he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a way to trye their ſpirits, by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of himſelfe: but thou haſt fully knowne my doctrine, manner of liuing purpoſe, faith long ſuffering, loue, patience. But indeede they ſit in the chaire of Moſes, as the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſies did 24. Mat. All thinges therefore which
<pb facs="tcp:17777:8"/> they ſhall command you obſerue and fulfil, but according to their workes do you not at all, for they ſay often and do not performe it. But to make any application of theſe I feare I ſhould looſe my labour, and ſing to ſuch an Adder as will neuer be charmed, though I ſing neuer ſo ſweetely: better is it therfore neuer to trouble my ſelfe at all, than to meddle with ſuch a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as can hardly be brought to paſſe, or to lay the ground worke before I caſt account whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I be able to builde or no, leſt that the ground worke being laid,, and I not able to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it my ſelfe, become ridiculous vnto al, and that were a great burthen for me.</p>
            <p>Now if a man will knowe certainely that hee hath a burthen, let him looke into the 7. of Ro. 7. Nay I knewe not ſinne but by the Law, for I had not knowne luſt, except the Lord had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not luſt. The knowledge therfore of our burthens cometh by the Lawe, not that we are vnder the Lawe, for now we are deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Law. But the knowledge of ſinne only cometh by the Law, which is the onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Law to driue a man to repentance.</p>
            <p>Now that not only the children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence haue a burthen, but alſo the elect children of God: it may appeare by the teſtimonie of Paul himſelfe in the 17. and 18. verſes. <hi>For I
<pb facs="tcp:17777:9"/> knowe that in me, that is, in my fleſhe dwelleth no good thing for will is preſent with me, but I finde no meanes to performe that which is good: for I do not that good which I would do, but the euil which I would not do, that do I.</hi> And ſo he concludes that euen the contagion of ſinne dwelleth in him, which is a grieuous and moſt hainous bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
            <p>And he that ſaith he hath no burthen, dccei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth himſelfe, and the trueh of God is not in him, as it is in the firſt Epiſtle of Iohn. 1. Chap. 8. ver. <hi>If we ſay that we haue no ſinne we deceiue our ſelues, and trueth is not in vs.</hi> And in the 2 Chap. He declares the meanes how to be eaſed of our burthen. If any man ſinne, wee haue an Aduocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt, the iuſt, and he is the reconciliation for our ſinnes, yet there is a difference between the ſinning of the godly and the vngodly. Sinning of the godly ſaid I, there be many partes of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that ſeeme repugnaunt to this: As firſt a good tree cannot bring foorth euill fruite. Hee that committeth ſinne is of the deuill, for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that is borne of God ſinneth not, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth: that which is borne of the ſpirit is ſpirite. Then how can the former ſtand for a trueth, that the children of God ſhoulde both ſinne, and not ſinne, haue a burthen, and
<pb facs="tcp:17777:9"/> haue none, when as we know euen by natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon, that two contraries cannot ſtand at one time in one ſubiect. Now in that the righteous do ſinne it is plaine, <hi>There is none that doth good, no not one,</hi> the righteous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſeuen times a day: and many ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The anſweare is very eaſie, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in deed do ſinne, but not vnto death, becauſe he is partely borne of God, and partly of a man, the firſt way he ſinneth not, the ſecond way hee ſinueth. Nohah GOD his faithfull and obedient ſeruant although the Lord bleſſed him, ſaying to his ſeede, bring ye foorth fruite, and multiplie, growe plentifully in the earth, and encreaſe therin. 9. Gen. 7. &amp; 9. verſes. <hi>Behold I euen I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh my couenant with you and your ſeede after you.</hi> Yet this waye hee ſinned not, but afterwardes it came to paſſe that he drunk of the wine, and was druncken, and vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered himſelfe in the middeſt of his Tent: ſee, that no ſoner he was come into the world but he was infected by it, and fell from God moſt ruenouſly, by which wee may gather, how ſlippery places we men of this worlde, ſtand in, ſo that it is impoſſible for vs to walke in it without danger of our liues. No
<pb facs="tcp:17777:10"/> maruaile therefore though we be as blind as beetles, that wee cannot ſee the ſunne-ſhine of righteouſneſſe, though it ſhine neuer ſo bright in England. O great and heauie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, in one houre able to cruſh downe our ſhoulders, and to caſt both body and ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lake of deſtruction: wee ſee therefore that Noah ſinned not the firſt way, but as he was man the ſecond way. Abraham, althogh he did forſake his owne countrey, and all his kindred, to goe to the land whereunto the Lord appointed him; in which he ſinned not becauſe it was Gods commaundement, but hee lyed, Gen. 12.13. in ſaying that his wife was his ſiſter for feare of the Aegyptians: Say I pray thee, that thou art my ſiſter, that I may fare well for thy ſake, and that my life may be preſerued by thee.</p>
            <p>And this ſecond way hee ſinned, becauſe his wife by this means was rauiſhed by Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao. Iacob the faithfull ſeruant of God, yet he deceiued his maſter in diuiding the flock. Gen. 30. the ſecond way hee ſinned. Dauid the annointed of God, yet notwithſtanding hee committed inceſt with Vrias wife, and therefore it was a heauie burthen vnto him: <hi>Sod quid onus?</hi> But what is the greateſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb facs="tcp:17777:10"/> Euen the loue of Idols. And firſt men make this world an Idoll, eſpecially wee of England, when wee like vnto Achabs wife are neuer content, though wee had neuer ſo much, yet ſtill we deſire more: and althogh (as M. Caluin ſaith) amongſt men there bee ſuch varietie of minds and deſires, that as it is a world to ſee them: yet do all agree in this point moſt plainly, that with whole hart and mind they are occupied in the world, &amp; the things therof: and ſurely his opinion is true and to be liked of all: for men nowadaies had rather eate the bread that periſheth, than drinke the water, whereof whoſoeuer ſhall drinke, out of his belly ſhall ſpring riuers of waters of life: not of ſuch waters as our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers drunke of in the rockes and died, but of the water of life, which neuer ſhall decay fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all eternities, and yet man moſt ſenſeles, had rather bee in bondage than in freedome, hee had rather drinke of the filthie puddles of Aegypt, to be fed with butter, beefe, vnions, or garlicke, than for to drinke of the water whoſe ſtreames flow from Iacob his well, or from the riuer of Eden: or to be fedde with Manna from heauen.</p>
            <p>Thus men become without vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb facs="tcp:17777:11"/> degenerating fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſonable creatures to ſenſe leſſe Idiots: and this is not the leaſt burthen we haue to beare in England. The Miniſters themſelues haue their burthen; <hi>Malumeſt nobis eſſe hîc:</hi> It is euill for vs to dwell here, for their portion is labour, a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy yoke laid vpon the ſons of Adam to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them thereby. If labour then be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the Miniſter to feed the flocke, then alſo he muſt haue his tools to finiſh the work as well for the body as for the mind.</p>
            <p>Now if the firſt ſort which concerneth his body be wanting, which is ſufficient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, then what hope is there of the giftes of the mind. For (as Ariſtotle affirmeth) the minde doth followe the temperature of the body, and the body it ſelfe cannot laſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out nouriſhment: then what ſhal we thinke of thoſe men that would deſtroy the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our Colleges to increaſe their own poſſeſſions, which be the well ſpringes of life to the whole land, confounding learning, &amp; bringing in barbariſme, by making the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God inferiour to the wiſedome of man? The word of God (ſay they) is ſimple, and may be vnderſtood without the Artes: which if it were true, doubtleſſe the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:17777:11"/> would neuer haue giuen commandement, that his Prieſts lips ſhould containe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or that the worde of God ſhould bee preached or that there ſhould be any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie at all, but theſe and ſuch like be the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions of ſathan, to deceiue the people in theſe laſt times.</p>
            <p>Now they which would haue done vs this harme, were not our open enemies, for then we could better haue eſpied them, and ſo eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed their malice: but it was our owne freends and familiars with whome wee haue walked in the houſe of God together, who went out from vs, but were not of vs, that moſt cruelly are bent againſt vs, and like vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naturall children deſtroy their owne deare mother, by whome they haue been broght vp, and cheriſhed; yet many of them wil cal for a learned miniſterye: but can any gather grapes of thornes, or figs of thriſtles? Can there bee any knowledge where there is no labour, or labour where there is no mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? No ſurely: for who would labour to become poore and baſe, and deſtitute of all things? or who would be a miniſter to haue the skin and the bone almoſt for apparell, ſo that he muſt take more care to preſerue
<pb facs="tcp:17777:12"/> life, than to inſtruct his people: being other wiſe condemned of the moſt? O what a wofull caſe is this? we hang our Harps vpon the trees, and ſit down by the waters of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon weeping, when we which are young ſchollers remember this Sion. And looke forth of our Studies with many ſalt teares, when we remember the vnmerciful dealing of theſe that with-holde our maintenaunce from vs. They may well bee compared to Pharaoh, for when the iudgement of God was great, and terrible in his land, that hee could not deny but it was the extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worke of God, yet for all this his hart was ſo hardened, that he could not be content to let the people go and ſerue the Lord, but v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this condition, that they ſhould leaue their ſubſtaunce for him, and his poſteritie: euen ſo the men of this worlde deale with the poote miniſters of God: for thogh their conſciences in keeping the maintenance of the Church, do accuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to call for a learned miniſtry, but proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſtill, they keepe their former poſſeſſions the ſpoile of the Church: No maruaile then if no reſidencye bee great in this land, when ſcarce two liuings wil find a man bread and
<pb facs="tcp:17777:12"/> apparel. Is there not greater fault in the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die cormorants of this worlde, who are the cauſes of all ſuche miſchiefe, than in thoſe that for neceſſitie and conſcience ſake, are conſtrained to take them, and ſurely there be manye that crye againſt it, but with no ground: for God knowes the ſimplicitie of many hartes, that haue two liuinges. The Miniſter is ſaid to be a feeder. 33. Ezechiel 1. and how can he feed others, when he can ſcarce feed himſelfe? How can his life and doctrine agree together? when the cares of this worlde do choake his minde.</p>
            <p>The children of Iſrael made Bricke by reaſon of their task-maiſters a long time, &amp; our Miniſters are fain to become ſeruile: yea &amp; as it were bond ſlaues, becauſe their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell task-maiſters with-hold their right, their children crie in the ſtreets being fatherleſſe, what ſtonie heart will not bleed at this, and deſire the Lord day and night till it be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? Which if it were, then all the outcries of our monſtrous hypocrites, men that cary the outward forme of godlineſſe, would ſoone ceaſe, that we might all agree in the ſpirit of truth, which is the bond of peace: that Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land might flouriſh and bee brought to all
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:17777:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:17777:13"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:17777:14"/> the Nations of the earth, as the Sunne in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect beautie: for want of diſcretion is the cauſe that hath cauſed ſo many libels to bee written againſt our auncient Fathers of the Church, who are indeede the reformers of ſuch abuſes, if euer they be reformed.</p>
            <p>This want of learning and Iudgement, doth cauſe them to ſhoote at al aduenturs, and to diſcouer the ſhame of their parents, if by any meanes poſſibly they could: ſuch graceleſſe children are nouriſhed &amp; broght vp in the boſome of this Church, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be cut off betim, it wil be a deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, for a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome deuided againſt it ſelfe can not ſtand. Nay, if any houſe be againſt it ſelfe it can not endure.</p>
            <p>If our realme be the one halfe papiſts, the other Browneſts, how can the goſpell take place in the hartes and conſcience of men, But that deſtruction, calamitie, and miſerie, ſhould come vpon the whole body. They preache peace indeede with their mouthes, but they haue ſwordes in their handes and hartes. They are like vnto the graue, faire without, but within full of rottenneſſe, and corruption.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:14"/>
            <p>The Crocodile ſeekes to ſee a man, but it is but to diſpatche him: and theſe men they would bring in reformation, to deform vs which liue in peace and quiet one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>Moyſes was full fortie yeeres olde before it came into his harte to viſite his brethren, but our yong heads will be ſcarce fourteen before they be medlers with the godly Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and fathers of our Church.</p>
            <p>The Boyes of Beyell muſt call balepate, balepate, ſo long till the beares deuour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, well take heed ye that be infected with that louen, for there is a rodde prepared for you, by the wiſedome of our gatious Prince, &amp; Councel. Did Paule euer reproue by libels? or, did the Apoſtles ſowe ſedicion by their doctrine? which 2. things doe argue in you the ſpirite of errour, the ſpirite of lyes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing the mindes of the people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their loyall obedience to their ſoueraigne Queen, but I warrant you, when they come to ryper yeeres, to try wiſedome got by experience, then they ſing cleane another ſong, &amp; turne the backeſide of the booke vpwards: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeareth, that they were braine ſicke in their youth, and a little giddie of the fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<pb facs="tcp:17777:15"/> their whole zeale, was but their vnbrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led affections, which did driue them on with cordes of vanity, to ſpeake euill of our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fathers: and thus many of them, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe being cured, haue confeſſed.</p>
            <p>Nowe where the fountaines is muddye what hope is there that the riuer ſhould bee cleere. If the miniſter be infected with this hereſie, then the people muſt needes be in a wofull caſe, for ſuch preache themſelues not the ſubſtance of the ſinceere and true doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</p>
            <p>The ignorant places are full of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Ephraim againſt Manaſſes, and Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt Ephraim: and euery Coblers ſtal is full of the controuerſies of the Church, &amp; all comes by yong vnlearned bablers, that of good meat giue the people nothing but a bone to gnawe of, and yet they muſt fight for it like dogs: yea, all the former euilles which I haue named, come of one euil, nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the wante of maintenuance for a learned miniſtery, which they ſo oft call for: would to God I had the tongue of men and Angelles to mollifie their heartes, that keepes it from the Church, and to write it therin with the pen of a Diamond. Nay, I am perſwaded
<pb facs="tcp:17777:15"/> that the Papiſts with their blinde deuotion towards the Church, ſhal riſe vp at the laſt day, and condempne vs profeſſed Chriſtians for our negligence heerein. They were neuer ſo forward in giuing to the Church, as wee are in taking from it, ſo that wee liue vppon the bloode of the people, and become fatte in wickednes, euen in the pleaſures of ſinne though they endure but for a ſeaſon: thus couetouſnes (deerly beeloued) when it crept into England, it did ſwallowe vp, and ſpoile the goods of the Church: but hearken ye deafe Adders, it is meete for you to dwell in your ſeeled houſes, and the houſe of God to ly waſte? 1. Hag.. And therefore it is that many of vs in England, haue ſowen muche, and bring in little; and haue eaten, but had not enough; drunke and were not filled; wee haue cloathed ourſelues, and yet we be not warme; and he that earneth wages hath put it in a broken bagge. Ye looked for much ſaith the Prophet, and loe it came to lyttle, and when ye brought it home, I did blowe vpon it ſaith the Lord, becauſe of my houſe that it is waſte, and ye run euery man to his owne houſe.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath placed vs heere, in a friut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:17777:16"/> land, and yet for this ſinne of robbing the Church, the dew of heauen did not fal vpon the earth to moiſten it, and ſo all our riches could not deliuer vs from great penury: thy deſtruction therefore is of thy ſelfe ô Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, repent therefore betime, runne not a whoring after thine owne inuentions, and now build a ſecond Church, farre more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then the firſt, and goe about it betime. The children of the Iewes were hindred, &amp; had many lets, becauſe they let ſlip the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie.</p>
            <p>Reſtore the goods of the Church bety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and you ſhall ſee if your little doe not encreaſe to aboundaunce, and then euerye ſtudent will labour for knowledge and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to benefit the Church, to the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Antichriſt, to the conforming and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ducting of your ſoules through the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this worlde, to the kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: this burthen if there were no moe in England, it were ſufficient to bring fire and brimſtone ſuddenlye to conſume vs, but at the preaching of Ionas the Niniuites repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted though his ſermon was very ſhorte, yet 40. daies, and Niniuie ſhall be deſtroyed &amp; turned the wreath of the Almightie cleane
<pb facs="tcp:17777:16"/> away from them. And it may bee likewiſe that the reading of this little Pamphlet will at the leaſt make ſome of them bluſh, when they conſider how many learned men they hinder, that are fain to ſtay ſtil in Cambridge for the great want that is in the Countrey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</p>
            <p>The Lord in times paſt had a controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with the children of Iſrael, becauſe there was no trueth, no mercie, no knowledge of God in their land. Oſe. 4.1. And what wil he doe with this mercileſſe nation, wherein by the wicked the Prophets are almoſt ſtoned, yet in the beſt part they are ſcourged and whipt by extreame penurie? VVill hee not haue a controuerſie with vs? and hath he not ſhewed tokens of it? Theſe laſt yeares when a mightie nation did riſe vp againſt vs like the ſandes of the ſea, though at that inſtant wee had ſome good motions, yet now when the peril is paſt, our hearts are hardened with Pharao, and we returne with the dogge to his vomit.</p>
            <p>Pharaoh had tenne mightie blowes at his heart, and yet would not be reclaimed, and England hath had a thouſand warnings, and yet ſtill is hardened. Moſes ſmit the rocke,
<pb facs="tcp:17777:17"/> and water guſhed out to the comforting of the children of Iſrael. And I would to God that teares of repentance might make ſuche men to weep day &amp; night for the deſolation of this Ieruſalem, and is it not a confuſion of our owne faces, that beeing vnder ſuch a moſt gratious Queene, by whoſe gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now this 33. yeeres wee haue enioyed all bleſſinges both ſpirituall and temporall, more than all our neighbor countreys about vs: that we (I ſay) ſhould deale ſo vngrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in with-holding the goodes of the Church, which by the bountifull hands of ſo gratious a Queene, and ſo prudent a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell is beſtowed vppon vs: and yet this burthen doth ſeeme to vs to bee ſo light, that we can wipe our mouthes, and ſay wee haue not ſinned. Let Fraunce confirme vs in this doctrine, for by this ſinne there came vp ſectes and hereſies, and had increaſed to a great and vnquenchable flame, had not the ſling of Dauid, and the ſword of Gedeon bene giuen into the Kings hand to fight the battell of the Almightie God for true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for the eſtabliſhing of the Church. Lord proſper his iourney, that through his hand Iſrael may be deliuered from Aegypt,
<pb facs="tcp:17777:17"/> where it lyeth in bondage vnder the Pope or vnder the Turke, &amp; that the God of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land may ſhew himſelfe to be the true God, and therefore that it is impoſſible for them to kicke againſt the pricke, or for duſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes to wage warre againſt the immortall &amp; euer-liuing God, whoſe power indeede no creature is able to reſiſt.</p>
            <p>I haue dwelt long (as you may ſee) in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth one of the burthens of this lande. But I may excuſe my ſelfe, for this one is all: and where this one is remooued, there all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther burthens may eaſily be taken away. So indeede it is a rocke of offence, a ſtone to ſtumble at, which except it bee taken out of out way, it is impoſſible that we ſhuld paſſe by it; except it be ſuch men as will ſtrayne a gnat, and ſwallow vp a cammell. And vnto theſe what is it but is poſsible, who can ſpeak to the Church out of euerie text all thinges? and theſe be they that condemn learning in Sermons, becauſe indeede they haue none themſelues. And this is the cauſe that the common people can better tell of cappe and ſurpleſſe, than of faith and a good conſcience which that ſect wants for the moſt part. Our Sauiour pronounced a woe to the Scribes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:17777:18"/> Phariſies, becauſe they were diligent in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing mint and rue, and euerie little trifle, leauing the weightier points of the lawe. But what if Chriſt were on the earth againe, doe you thinke they ſhould eſcape with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand woes, becauſe they haue beene the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of many mens ſouls, driuing them to deſperation, as by wofull experience wee ſee it daily, and all for want of learning? Such deale with our auncient Fathers writings as they that haue cutte a purſe, who takes the mony, and caſts the purſe away, for fear their wickednes ſhould be knowne to the world: and they, for all that they cannot abide our Fathers, yet they are faine to flie to their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings to releeue their neceſsitie, yet they caſt away the purſe. But all is for vaineglorie to ſet out themſelues, as though it were theyr owne inuentions, or their owne arme which helped them. Thus they ſet at varience the minds of the people: one holding of Apollo, another of Paul, &amp; the third of Cephas; one of this man, another of that man: which things except they be lookt too in time, doe foretell the ruine of the Church to come. And though by reaſon of our moſt gratious Queene it come not in our dayes, yet it may
<pb facs="tcp:17777:18"/> come in the time of our poſteritie, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are to come to the end of the world; and though our life be ſhort, or lighter than vanitie, becauſe our dayes are numbred, yet let vs worke thoſe thinges in this ſhort life, which may bring vs to immortalitie, where wee ſhall neuer carry any more burthens, but ſing praiſes of the moſt high continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And foraſmuch as our life while wee liue in this worlde is ſubiect to many trials and temptations, as alſo that man euen againſt himſelfe is alwaies fighting, the powers of his minde and body are alwaies at defiance one with the other, let vs therefore labor againſt our fleſh, that the ſpirit of error do not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn vs. Lucifer being the chiefeſt Angel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would be equal with his maker, was caſt downe into the loweſt place in hell; but theſe men will ſit in the iudgement ſeate of God, and crie damnation, damnation, as if they had ſome ſecrete inſpiration from the Lords counſell. But will not God caſt them downe? Will hee not confound their pride, that pul motes out of their brothers eye, but forget the beames which is in their owne? Yet I ſpeake not this to defend non reſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: for as there be that may iuſtly ſay, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
<pb facs="tcp:17777:19"/> eſt nobis eſſe hîc:</hi> So there are alſo that think it a pleaſant life though they haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient maintenance for their degree in the country abroad to liue at eaſe, and ſo in their life they expreſſe this ſaying; <hi>Bonum eſt nobis eſſe hîc.</hi> It is an eaſie life to liue here. I muſe how they bluſh not when men call them Miniſters, when indeed they neuer do mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and theſe men are alwayes learning, and neuer come to any perfection: and if they take neuer ſo great pains to the outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of men, yet for all this, they are like vnto the candle, which beeing put vnder a buſhell, giueth ſmall light or none at all. O what greeuous burthens are in England, whereof this is not the leaſt: for ſuch liue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the bloud of the ſlaine of the people.</p>
            <p>Thoſe therefore that bee guiltie in this, I accuſe none, I ſpeake it generally to all, lette them take heede of it: and I would to God that euen in this their day they would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the time of their viſitation, and ſo they would (conſidering the night is paſt, and the day is come) put away the workes of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and put on the armour of light.</p>
            <p>The husbandman of whome the parable conſiſteth in the Goſpell, after hee had once
<pb facs="tcp:17777:19"/> dreſſed the trees of his garden, amongſt the which, in one he had moſt delight and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tooke more paines in pruning of it, than of the other, ſuppoſing indeed to haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the moſt fruite at it: but when the time came, beholde there was nothing vppon it but leaues. Then at the requeſt of his ſeruant he let it ſtand another yere, and at the time appointed looked for fruit, and lo there was nothing. Then the husbandman ſaide, the third yeare cut it down, leaſt it alſo make the ground barren.</p>
            <p>The Lord our God, who by his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and goodnes hath planted vs in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous vineyard, and hath taken great paines in pruning of vs, hath looked for fruite, but behold the bitter rootes of diſſention. Now the Lorde expecting daily our amendment, hath let vs ſtand ſtill in the floriſhing vine, not for three yeeres, but for 20. or 30. and aboue, and yet behold no fruite but leaues in the beſt part, or elſe wilde grapes good for nothing but the furnace: Now what iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment remaineth, but that we ſhould be cut vp, leaſt wee alſo make the country and the people barren amongſt whom we liue. But I fear me this long forbearing is but to bring a
<pb facs="tcp:17777:20"/> greater deſtruction, and as a man would ſay to fetch his blow the further, that his ſtroke may be the greater.</p>
            <p>By this which is ſpoken, you may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue, that euery man both by nature, &amp; by the courſe of his life, hath a great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. But there be many mo burthens beſide theſe, for vſurie is a burthen. The Vſurer can ſay for the defence of himſelfe, I do nothing but that which the lawe will allow, although indeed vnder a pretence of lawe hee meane moſt deceitfully. But you knowe that Iudas vnder a pretence of holines betraied his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and ſo thoſe Vſurers eate vp the people ſucking the bloud of them, and all this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour and pretence of lawe: But though euerie one do ſinne, and haue a great burthen: yet notwithſtanding as a broken peece of gold is not to bee caſt away, ſo wee ſhould beare with the infirmities of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, helping their weaknes: &amp; ſo it would followe, that we ſhould beare one anothers burthen; for he that ſeemes to ſtand, let him take heed that he fall not. 1. Cor. 10.12. Thy brother fell to day, thou maieſt fall to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: for there ſhall bee iudgement merciles to him that ſheweth no mercie, and mercie
<pb facs="tcp:17777:20"/> reioyceth againſt iudgement. 2. Iam. 13. Let vs therfore be merciful as our Sauiour Chriſt is merciful, for Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſinnes. 1. Pet. 3.18. The grace of God hath appeared vnto all. 2. Titus. 11. Inſtructing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with meeknes, that are contrary minded prouing that if God at anye tyme will giue them repentaunce, that they may know the trueth. 2. Tim. 2.25.</p>
            <p>So that ye ſee the burthens of men bee infinite, and yet men not to bee reiected for their burthens, for vnder a filthye and polluted skin may be a full ſound body, &amp; vnder vice may lurke excellent vertue. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena, as Poets faine, had a mole in her cheek which made her more amiable: ſo that vice doth rather adorne, then any way diſhonor the ſubiect in ſome, neither is the Lord his hand ſhortned, that it can not make an euill tree bring forth good fruit, for he that made the eye, will ye not haue him ſee? and hee which made the eare, will ye not haue him heare? Hee which created man can hee not change man which way he will, who hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Kings heart in his hands, as ſayeth Salomon to diſpoſe &amp; turne as pleaſeth him beſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:21"/>
            <p>But I will let this point paſſe, and come to the ſecond thing which I promiſed in the beginning to ſpeake of, that as euery one hath a burthen, (as you haue heard before) ſo euery one muſt beare his owne burthen. The ſoule which ſinneth ſhall die. 18. Ezec. 20. The fathers ſhal not be put to death, for the children, nor the children put to death for the fathers: but euery man ſhal be put to death for his owne ſinne. 24. Deut. 16. So then euerye one of vs ſhall giue accountes of himſelfe to God. 14. Rom. 12. By which two places it doth appeare without all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, that euery man ſhall beare his own burthen. But ſome may obiect (fleſh and blood is ready to make obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as did Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodemus, howe can a man ſaid he be borne again) alleaging a place of ſcripture againſt this doctrine, out of the 20. of Exod. 5. viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the iniquitie of the fathers vnto the children, vppon the 3. and 4. generation of them that hate me. Adam ſinned, and ſo we all are puniſhed. 3. Ge. Achabs wiues, ſinne brought deſtruction vpon all their Kinred. Hammon ſinned, and all his houſe was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
            <p>Dauid ſinned (as I ſaid before) and all
<pb facs="tcp:17777:21"/> his Realme was puniſhed with a ſore peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. If this then be ſo, as it is moſt ſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord hath ſpoken it, then how can this ſtand? The former is taken for eternall puniſhment of God after this life, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for temporal and momentary puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and thoſe the Lord layeth often on one man for the ſinne of another; and the ſchoolmen giues very good reaſon for it, but eſpeciallie <hi>Thomas Aquinus, quia vnus res eſt alterius,</hi> 2. <hi>propter periculum imitationis.</hi> And althogh the ſchoole men in very many pointes erre, yet in theſe they haue ſaid moſte truely: for both man is prone vnto ſinne by nature, and alſo verye eaſilye bent vnto it by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of others, <hi>nam exemplum eſt alteranatura</hi> as one ſaith verie wiſely. But there is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment eternal, and in this euery one ſhal beare his owne burthen: for he that ſinneth ſhall die.</p>
            <p>The wicked in deed may flooriſhe for a time, but it can be no long ſpace, the chaffe may growe with the wheat, but it is but til Harueſt.</p>
            <p>Dauid at the firſt ſight of the wicked thought that they had been the onely men, but when he went into the houſe of God, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:17777:22"/> there did conſider the end of theſe men, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he concluded, and ſaid, that his foote had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſlipped: For they ſhall ſoone bee cut downe like graſſe, and ſhall wither, as the greene herbe. 37. Pſal. 2. The worme ſhal feele his ſweetenes, he ſhall bee no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and the wicked ſhall bee broken down like a tree. 24. Iob. 20. But wherfore do the wicked liue and wax olde, and growe in wealth? There ſeede is eſtabliſhed in their fight with them, and their generations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eies; Their houſes are peacable without feare; and the rodde of God is not vpon them; Their Bullockes gendereth and failleth not; their Cowe calues, and caſteth not her Calfe. 21. Ioh. 7, 8, 9, 10. ve. He will deuide their leaues in his wreath, they ſhal be as ſtubble Before the winde, &amp; as chaffe that the ſtorme carieth away. 17, &amp; 18. ve.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what an euill bargaine the wicked make in this life, for temporall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they haue eternall paine: and for the things of this world, they looſe the euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyes of heauen, and this is not onelye a great burthen, but euery man ſhall beare his owne burthen for this cauſe.</p>
            <p>And thus I haue in ſome meaſure fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:17777:22"/> my promiſe, nowe it remaineth that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ground worke laid, I ſhould goe on and finiſh the building, and ſurely where do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine goes not before, their exhortation ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take no place: for as the building cannot ſtand without the foundation, no more can exhortation, without doctrine, but lyke to the houſe builded vppon the ſandes, which when the raine came, fell, and the fall therof was great: the winde blewe it downe, and why? becauſe it was not builded vppon a rock, and had no ſure foundation.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this doctrine ſerueth to al e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and degrees of this life, and ſeing that euery man hath a burthen, ſom greater, ſom leſſe, according to their ſinnes; and in al ſome it behoueth vs therfore with ſpeed to come neere to the proclamation made by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt: Come all you that be heauye loden, and I will eaſe you, for ſo hee loued the world, that he gaue himſelfe for it. Thou therfore that art a Miniſter, do thy office tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, eat not vp thy flocke by making vſurie v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, and conſider the laſt words in our Sauiours will: Peter loueſt thou me? feede my flock, or if thou loueſt me, feed my flock. The ſame he repeted three times moſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently,
<pb facs="tcp:17777:23"/> which ſurely doeth argue the great neceſſitie of it.</p>
            <p>And though men haue arrowes in their tongues, and ſhoot at thee by euill reportes, yet if thou be diligent, thou ſhalt haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, for the day will come, and it is not far off, wherein euery man muſt beare his owne burthen.</p>
            <p>It ſerueth alſo for a ſinguler vſe to the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie, that care be had of ſufficient men, for the diſchargeing of the duty of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye; ſuch men, who reſemble the trees of Perſia, that are alwayes budding, and haue alwaies ripe fruite on them, as Theophra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus witneſſeth: Such as woulde inſtruct the people of God, giuing them ripe &amp; whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine, fir for the eating. But alas there is a great want of this, which is a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthen to vs heere in England. The wiſemen of our time are become yong chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the olde grayheaded ancient men, are become yong Schollers: and what is my meaning; but as I ſaid before, that ſuch are al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waies learning, and neuer come to anye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. I meane not the Reuerend fathers of our Church, who take great paines in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of vs, but of ſuch as will neuer be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
<pb facs="tcp:17777:23"/> But what a fearefull and dangerous thing this is, in that day will appeare, wherin euery man ſhall beare his owne burthen.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore (dearely beloued) bee true harted one to another, and pluck the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſardes of hipocriſie from our faces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we haue bene couered a long time, and ſo ſpeaking the trueth from our hartes, wee may in that day be iuſtified, wherein euerie man muſt beare his owne burthen. And let vs not ſuffer the people to ſtatue, for want of teaching, as wofull experience doeth ſhowe the like in this Church of England, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the North partes, who for want of preaching, liue in darknes, &amp; in the ſhadowe of death, ſuch ſcarſcitie there is of thoſe that ſhoulde guide their feete into the waye of peace.</p>
            <p>The Lord graunt that we of our Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, who liue by the ſweate of their browes, be not plagued for it in that day wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie man muſt beare his owne burthen. But you that be rich, withdraw not your minds from Chriſt, by reaſon of aduerſitie, which is incident to the Goſpell, bee not content to do onely thoſe things which you may with caſe, or with the commoditie of this life; for
<pb facs="tcp:17777:24"/> ſo did the yong man: but when Chriſt came at this; Sell all that thou haſt and giue to the poore, then hee went away from Chriſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull: for why, he had great poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>And I feare if a triall ſhould come, we that now are the greateſt poſſeſſors, would then be the leaſt, and turne away from Chriſt, for why wee haue great poſſeſſions: and ſo it would go euill on our partes euen in the day wherin euery man muſt beare his own bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. And you alſo for whom I haue cauſed this litle exhortation to be put in print, that burthen your ſelues with the curſe of the Church, and with Ananias defraud his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of their right; now at the laſt awake out of your dreame, ſuffer not your eye lids to ſleepe, nor the temples of your heade to take any reſt, vntill you haue reſtored that which you haue wilfully and wrongfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. And now, euen now kiſſe the ſonne leaſt he bee angrie, and ſo yee periſh euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly: If his wrath be kindled, yea but a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, woe be vnto you: it had beene better for you that you had neuer beene borne, or that a milne ſtone had beene tyed about your necke, and beene caſt into the ſea; for in that day of the wrath of the Lord, the hils wil not
<pb facs="tcp:17777:24"/> couer you, the fire will not conſume you, the water will not deuoure you, but euerie one ſhall receiue iudgement, and no meanes to eſcape, euen in that day wherein euery man muſt beare his owne burthen.</p>
            <p>This exhortation might be inlarged fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the beating downe of euery parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſinne in the whole life of man, but that would require whole volumes, and not the ſhortnes of this Pamphlet. Heere therefore I will make an ende, deſiring God that hee will forgiue vs our ſinnes, that he would bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie them in the death of his Sonne, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie our euill affections, that ſo wee beeing dead vnto ſinne, may liue vnto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and be found blameleſſe before God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in that day, wherein euery man muſt beare his owne burthen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:25"/>
            <head>A praier.</head>
            <p>OPen our eyes (O Lord) that we may bee turned from darkneſſe to light, from the power of Satan to thee our God. Open the harts and eares of vs thy people here in England, that we may imbrace this comfortable doctrine: for Paul may plant, and Apollo water, but it is the Lord of life that giueth the increaſe. We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore flie to thy throne of mercie (moſt mighty &amp; moſt mercifull Father) beſeeching thee to heare vs for Christ his ſake, pardoning and forgiuing vs all our ſinnes, which bee the cauſes why thou wilt not heare our praiers, and graunt our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, except they be wiped away in his bloud. Build thou Ieruſalem in euerie one of our harts, and gather our wicked affections into the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of Iſrael. And foraſmuch as this our land hath lately beene troubled with great contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all proceeding from the pride of our hearts, now therefore (good Lorde) after this great tempeſt ſend a gratious calme, and after this long warre ſend vs euerlaſting peace towards the kingdome of heauen, through the merits of Chriſt Ieſus our onely Lord and Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17777:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
